Guide to the Max J. and Ruth Clement Bond Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Max J. and Ruth Clement Bond papers,
1912-2004
[Bulk dates: 1930-1990].
Bond, J. Max.
32 linear ft. (42 Boxes: 17 document boxes, 23 record cartons, 1 over-sized box, 1 small box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1473
7031632
This collection contains the papers of J. Max Bond, Sr. (1902-1991), educator, State Department and United States Agency for International Development (USAID) official and president of the University of Liberia, and Ruth Clement Bond (1904-2005), chair of the English Department at Kentucky State College and at the University of Liberia, and president of the African-American Women’s Association. The collection includes extensive family and professional correspondence, writings, and documents relating to educational, political, community and civil rights organizations in which the Bonds participated. The collection also contains photographs and ephemera.
Biographical Note
James Max Bond, Sr. and Ruth Elizabeth Clement Bond, husband and wife, both hailed from prominent and well-educated African-American families.
J. Max Bond, Sr., State Department and United States Agency for International Development (USAID) official and president of the University of Liberia, was born in Nashville, Tennessee on September 15, 1902. His father, James M. Bond (1863-1929), a Congressional Minister and community leader served as the first director of the Kentucky Commission on Interracial Cooperation. After graduating from the Oberlin College Theological Seminary in 1893, James Bond married Jane A. Browne, who was also a graduate of Oberlin. Together they had six children, including Max Sr.
Ruth Elizabeth Clement was born in Louisville, Kentucky on May 22, 1904. Her father, George Clinton Clement was a bishop in the African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church; in 1946 her mother, Emma Clarissa Williams Clement, became the first African-American woman to be named American Mother of the Year. Both of Ruth's parents were graduates of Livingstone College and her father also had an LL.D. from Wilberforce University. Ruth was one of seven children.
Max Sr. graduated from the High School Department of Simmons University in Louisville, Kentucky in 1921 and attended the Lincoln Institute. After graduation, he moved to Chicago, where, from 1922 to 1926, he earned his B.P.E. from George Williams College (known today as Roosevelt University). While pursuing his degree, Max also worked as the director of the Oakland School Playground from 1923 until 1925. From 1926 to 1928 he was employed as physical education director at the Pittsburgh YMCA, before earning an M.A. in Education and Educational Administration at the University of Pittsburgh in 1930. Between 1929 and 1931 Max also served as the director of the Kentucky Interracial Commission.
Ruth, like her parents, attended Livingstone College, but received both her B.A. (1925) and an M.A. (1930) from Northwestern University where she majored in English Literature and Sociology. In the years between acquiring her degrees, Ruth taught English at Louisville Central High School and from 1930 to 1932 she was head of the English Department at Kentucky State College.
In 1931 Max and Ruth Clement married and moved to Los Angeles where Max was enrolled in a doctoral program at the University of Southern California (USC). Although Ruth also began graduate studies at USC, she suspended her formal academic pursuits shortly after the birth of the Bonds' first child in 1933. Max received his Ph.D. in Sociology in 1936 with a dissertation entitled "The Negro in Los Angeles." Upon obtaining his doctorate, Max embarked on a career as an educator. His first position, from 1934-1938, was with the Tennessee Valley Authority as Director of Negro Personnel and Education. Ruth became known for her Tennessee Valley Authority quilt designs, which were sewn by the wives of African-American men who built dams for the TVA in the mid-1930s. Next, Max served as Dean of Dillard University in New Orleans, Louisiana (1938-1940); from 1940-1944 he was employed as Dean of the School of Education at the Tuskegee Institute (today Tuskegee University).
In 1944 the first of Max and Ruth's foreign sojourns began: Max accepted a job with the US State Department's Inter-American Educational Foundation in Port-au-Prince, Haiti, where he served as director of the educational mission and Ruth was on the faculty of L'Ecole Normale de Martissant. The Bonds left Haiti in 1947 when Max was appointed Dean of the Graduate School of Education of Clark Atlanta University. In 1950 the State Department sent the Bonds to Liberia, where Max, following a reorganization of the University of Liberia, became the university's first President and Ruth headed the English Department. The Bonds enjoyed a close working relationship with Liberian President William Tubman.
Max's stint in Liberia lasted until 1955, at which point he began his work as an official in the United States Agency for International Development (USAID). Max's first appointment was as Education Advisor to Afghanistan's Minister of Education; next he took up a similar role in Tunisia. Just as he had done in Liberia, Max played a role in the reorganization of Kabul University and the University of Tunis. In 1960 the Bonds returned to the United States, taking up residence in Washington, D.C. briefly, before spending a year in Sierra Leone. Max's final tour of duty was in Nyasaland (now Malawi), where he organized teacher training programs. Following his retirement in 1966, Max joined Ruth in becoming active in community issues in the D.C. area. During the 1960s Ruth served as President of the African-American Women's Association, and in 1978 she was part of a National Council of Negro Women fact-finding mission that studied the role of women in Senegal, Togo, and the Ivory Coast.
Other educators in the extended Clement and Bond families included Ruth's brother, Rufus Early Clement, and Max Sr.'s brother, Horace Mann Bond. Rufus E. Clement was a long-time president of Atlanta University. Horace Bond, author of The Education of the Negro in American Social Order, served as the first African-American President of Lincoln University, as well as the head of the Bureau of Education and Social Research at Atlanta University. He also co-founded the Africa-America Institute, an organization with which Max Sr. and Ruth were closely involved.
The Bonds had three children, all of whom followed their parents' educational lead. Jane Emma Clement Bond (b. 1933), who received her Ph.D. from University College, London University, became a professor of European History and Modern France at Baruch College; J. Max Bond, Jr. (1935-2009), an architect and Columbia University professor, was a graduate of Harvard University; and George Clement Bond (b. 1936), obtained his Ph.D. from the London School of Economics and was the Director of the Institute for African Studies at Columbia University, as well as a Professor of Anthropology at Teachers College.
Max died in 1991and Ruth in 2005.
Scope and Content
The J. Max and Ruth Clement Bond Papers consist of the personal and professional writings, correspondence, photographs, and financial and legal records of the couple. Of particular interest are Max Bond's professional documents and reports, and correspondence related to education in, and United States assistance to, African nations, especially Liberia and Nyasaland (present-day Malawi). The collection also includes a large amount of printed material related not only to Max Bond's career with the University of Liberia, the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), and the US Department of State, but also to the couple's wide commitment to civil rights, political activism, and various community organizations. Among these printed materials, particularly well represented organizations are the African-American Institute and the many women's organizations with which Ruth Bond worked, including the Association of American Foreign Service Women, Church Women United, and International Women's Year, 1975.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1930s-1992, 2004
Series II: Country, Regional and Subject Files, 1935-1995
Subseries II.1: Country and Regional, 1939-1990
Subseries II.2: Subject Files, 1935-1995
Series III: Writings, 1930-1988
Series IV: Organizations, 1942-1995
Series V: Personal, 1914-1992
Subseries V.1: General, circa 1914-1995
Subseries V.2: Daybooks, Diaries, Notebooks and Personal Documents, 1925-1995
Subseries V.3: Financial, 1931-1994
Series VI: Photographs, 1912-1990s
Subjects
African-American Institute.; Boys and Girls Club of Greater Washington.; Association of American Foreign Service Women.; Church Women United.; National Council of Women of the United States.; National Council of Negro Women.; United States.--Agency for International Development.; University of Liberia.; Widening Horizons (Washington, D.C.); World Day of Prayer International Committee.; World Conference of the United Nations Decade for Women: Equality, Development, and Peace (1980 :--Copenhagen, Denmark).; Bond, George C.; Bond, J. Max.; Bond, J. Max Jr.; Bond, Jane Clement; Bond, Ruth.; Bond, Ruth.; Geographic; Black power--United States--History--20th century.; International Women's Year, 1975.; Genre; Occupation
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
One folder: Box 33, folder 3, is restricted until 2032.
Acquisition
Jane Clement Bond Gift 2008
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
J. Max Bond, Jr. Papers at Avery Architecture and Fine Arts Archives, Columbia University Library
- Series I: Correspondence, 1934-1992, 2004
  This series contains correspondence pertaining to J. Max Bond’s career as a member of United States Agency for International Development (US AID) and the United States Foreign Service, Ruth Bond’s affiliation and leadership of various women’s organizations, letters from the immediate and extended family, and a few Bond family financial and legal materials.
  General Correspondence includes letters to and from a wide variety of professional associates and Bond family members, as well as more occasional correspondents. Amongst the general correspondence can be found letters and cards from Ruth’s brother, Rufus Clement, and sister, Abbie; Max’s brothers Gilbert and Horace; and a number of nephews, nieces, and other extended family members, including Georgia State Senator Julian Bond. This correspondence has been arranged chronologically by decade, and runs from the 1930s through the 1990s.
  Correspondence from the immediate family includes letters to and from sons Max Jr. and George, and daughter Jane. This material, the majority written during the late 1950s and 1960s, contains extensive correspondence pertaining to Max’s and George’s secondary and university education, and many of these letters are copies written by Max Sr. to his sons from his various USAID and Foreign Service postings. Because much of the correspondence is addressed to both George and Max, Jr., their correspondence has been generally kept together, with the exception of a large group of letters addresses specifically to Max Jr. The Jane Bond correspondence primarily contains letters to her parents from the 1950s through the 1990s. The Max Bond, Jr. and George Bond correspondence, as well as the Jane Bond correspondence has been organized chronologically by decade.
  Note: Some correspondence, both professional and occasionally personal, can also be found in the Subseries II.1: Country and Regional, 1939-1990.
  - General, 1930s-1990s, Undated (11 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 11)
  - General, 1930s-1990s, Undated (9 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 9)
  - General, 1930s-1990s, Undated (8 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 8)
  - General, 1930s-1990s, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Family
    - Max and Ruth Bond--Personal, circa 1934-1978, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - George and Max Bond, Jr., 1948-1970s (8 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 4 to 11)
    - George and Max Bond, Jr., 1948-1970s (7 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Max Bond, Jr.--University, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Jane Bond, 1950s-1960s (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Jane Bond, 1970s-1990s (7 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Jane Bond, 1970s-1990s (3 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Family Reunion, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Professional and Organizational
    - General, 1961-1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Afghanistan, 1954-1957, 1978, Undated (6 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 6 to 11)
    - Afghanistan, 1954-1957, 1978, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - African American Institute, 1978-1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Atlanta University, 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Haiti, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Howard University, 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Institute of Computer Technology, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Liberia, 1950-1978 (6 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 7 to 12)
    - Liberia, 1950-1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Malawi (formerly Nyasaland), 1961-1967 (5 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 2 to 6)
    - Malawi (formerly Nyasaland)--and Travel Documents, 1963-1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Sierra Leone, 1953-1962, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Senator Heinz 1982 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Tunisia, 1957-1960, Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Tunisia, 1957-1960, Undated, (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Women’s Organizations, 1960s-1990 (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 4 to 6)
    - “Young, Andrew”, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Legal and Financial
    - General, 1940s-1980s (4 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 8 to 11)
    - Fundraising and Contributions, 1975-1979 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Lawsuit--Amtrak, 1975-1989 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Lawsuit--Police Brutality, 1989-1992 (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Lawsuit--Police Brutality--Notes, 1989, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Jackson, Abbie--Estate, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Invitations
    - General, 1949-1990 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Professional, 1951-1990 (5 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 2 to 6)
- Series II: Country, Regional and Subject Files, 1935-1995
  Included here are reports, documents, and printed materials related to the countries in which the Bonds worked and toured, and their various interests and avocations. The material in this series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Subseries II.1: Country and Regional, 1939-1990
    The bulk of the material in this subseries is related to the countries and regions in which Max Bond worked while employed by the United States Department of State and the United States Agency for International Development (USAID). Materials include reports—many of which were written by Max Bond—correspondence, printed material and ephemera. Printed materials include a small collection of Liberian newspapers, several broadsides of Liberian government proclamations, pamphlets, newspapers, and brochures—published by various African states as well as the US State Department. Also here are Ruth Bond's notes and report of her trip to West Africa in 1978. The trip, a feasibility study, was sponsored by the International Division of the National Council of Negro Women. Some correspondence, both professional and occasionally personal, can also be found here.
    - Afghanistan
      - Basic Data, 1956, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Description--Draft, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Education--Reports, 1952, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Ephemera, 1955, Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - "Proverbs, 100 Afghan Persian"--Christy Wilson, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Reports, 1955-1957, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Reports--Ill Treatment, 1956, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Reports--Terminal, 1962, Undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Africa
      - General, 1954-1989 (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 5 to 7)
      - American Aid--Proposals, 1975-1983, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Education--Charts and Statistics, 1966, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - Education Notes, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Memos and Reports, 1957-1962, Undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Printed Material, 1960s-1970 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Report--Draft--International Institute of African Guidance and Development, circa 1960s (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Trip to--Ruth Bond's Report, 1978 (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Cuba--"A Public Survey on the Quality of Health Care," 1988 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Haiti, 1945-1947, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Haiti--Printed Material, 1945-1946 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - India--Education--Reviews, 1955-1956 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Indochina, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Korea--United States Policy, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Lebanon--Education--Proposal, circa 1950s (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - "Lebanon, Letters From"--Edward Marion Hope, 1951-1966 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Liberia
      - General, 1972-1990 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Description--Draft, Undated (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Ephemera, 1950-1954 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Ephemera--Programs and Bulletins, 1950-1954 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - "Folktales of the Liberian Tribes"--Charles S. G. Boayue, Undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Manly, Arthur Nanuh--Report of Trip to the United States, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Periodicals, 1950-1954 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Proclamation, 1954 (Box 41, Folder 2)
      - Sketch--University of Liberia Amphitheatre, Undated (Box 41, Folder 3)
      - Trip to--Notes, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Tubman, William, 1951-1954, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - University of--Bulletin, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - University of--English Theses--Students of Ruth Bond, 1953-1954 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - University of--Yearbooks, 1952-1954 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Malawi (formerly Nyasaland)
      - "An AID Employee in Nyasaland," 1962-1964 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Controversy, Textbook Distribution, 1964-1965, Undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Printed Material, 1964-1973 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Reports, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Reports--Education, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Reports--End of Tour, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Maps, Undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Namibia--Printed Material, 1960s-1970 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Nigeria--Printed Material, Circa 1950s (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Senegal--Trip to--Notes, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Sierra Leone
      - Education--Proposal, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Ephemera, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - "--Old and New of," 1939 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Reports, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - South Africa, 1978-1990 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - South Africa--Printed Material, 1978-1979 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Sudan--Printed Material, 1976-1978 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Tanzania--Printed Material, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Togo--Trip to, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Tunisia
      - American Women's Club of, 1957-1959 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Education--Report, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Ephemera, 1957-1959 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - University Proposal, Undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Uganda--Printed Material, Undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - United States--State Department
      - Bulletins, 1969-1986 (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 7 to 8)
      - Employees of African Descent, 1965-1966, Undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Program Training, Circa 1960s (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - West Africa--Observations of, Circa 1952-1954 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - West Africa--Printed Material, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Zambia--Printed Material, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II.2: Subject Files, 1935-1995
    This subseries features an eclectic mix of personal and vocational interests of both Max and Ruth Bond. Included are materials produced by or regarding the extended Bond-Clement family. Areas of vocational interest comprise the Tennessee Valley Association, the Tuskegee Institute, various educational topics and the Washington, DC community.
    Max Bond's clipping folders, which contained un-annotated newspaper and magazine articles primarily from mainstream media sources such as the New York Times, the Washington Post, Time, The New Republic and The Nation, and mostly dating from the late 1960s and early 1970s, were not retained. Selected folder headings, created by Max Bond, give an indication of the subjects that he collected: "Africa," "African Jewelry," "Art-Theatre-Agriculture," "Black Colleges," "Black Education," "Black Intelligence," "Black Male Crisis," "Black Politicians," "Black Power," "Black Related Recent Current," "Black Vote," "Black and White Together Movements," "Blacks/Africa," "Blacks in Nixon’s Employ," "Church," "Civil Rights," "Criminals," "Grenada’s Rape-Rush’s Rule," "Impeachment," "Indians + Other Minorities," "Rev Jackson," "Jaworski," "Job Discrimination," "Justice Dpmt. Violation," "Kent State," "Martin L King," "Medicare," "Myth + Sham," "NAACP," "Negro + Other Leaders," "Nixon-Agnew + Hiss," "Outstanding Blacks/Black Leaders," "Panthers," "Police Brutality," "Politics Reagan’s Fall," "RACIAL: Whites + Blacks," "South African White Churches," "Snow 1987," "Student Protest Groups," "Wallace of Alabama," "What Citizens Should Know," and "Wine + Foods."
    - African-Asian-American Peoples Organization--Proposal, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - "The African Influence on Afro-American Art"--Lois Jones Pierre Noel, Circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - African Methodist Episcopal (AME) Zion Church, 1968-1975 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Afro-Americans Problems Conference--Proposal, Circa 1965 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Bond, Horace--"From Negro to American Man"--Address to Lincoln College, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Bond, Horace--"A Study of Factors Involved in the Identification and Encouragement of Unusual Academic talent Among Under Privileged Populations," 1967 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Bond, Julian--Clippings, 1969-1979 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Bond, Julian--Remarks: Anniversary of Fair Housing Act, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Bond, Zelema--Proposal--Supportive Educational Services, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Boston--African-American Research, 1987-1988, Undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Brann, Joan--State Department Appointment, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Clothing--Patterns, Circa 1950s (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Clement, Rufus E., 1947, 1967-1969 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Clement, Rufus E--Audio Tape--Shining Light Award, 1968 (Box 42)
    - The Committee for the Future--SYNCON Booklet, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Eckhardt, Celia--Feminism, Undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Education
      - General, 1965-1967, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - "The Evaluation of Higher Institutions," 1937 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - International Students--Africa, 1962, 1981, Undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - International Students--Printed Material, 1966-1981 (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - International Students--Reports, Circa 1970s-1980 (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - Knoxville People's College--Proposal, Undated (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - Louisiana--Reports, 1937-1940 (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Phoenix Indian School, 1972-1973 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Teacher Education Questionnaire, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - U. S. Commission on Civil Rights--Testimony of Arthur S. Fleming, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - University of the District of Columbia, 1981, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Diplomatic Lists, 1966-1979 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - Funerals, 1960s-1990s (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - Home Repair, Circa 1960s-1971 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - International Glass Plant, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 25)